A Guide to the Virginius Dabney Papers, 1880-1970
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Virginius Dabney 1880-1970
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7690-r
This collection consists of 3 boxes of papers.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited on 24 April 1973.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of Virginius Dabney contain extensive correspondence carried on by Dabney as editor of the Richmond Times-Dispatch, in his personal life, and as a Pulitzer Prize- winning author. Other materials deal with his books such as Below the Potomac, The Dry Messiah, and Liberalism in the South, and much useful material collected as research material for these books is present. There is extensive material on the American Society of Newspaper Editors which Dabney served in various capacities including president. A great deal of useful material on race relations, African Americans, the N.A.A.C.P., etc., is present. Recent political history of Virginia is strongly represented in Dabney's correspondence as editor of Virginia's leading newspaper, and in his personal correspondence with figures such as Senator A. Willis Robinson, Francis Pickens Miller, and Senator Carter Glass.
Contents List
- Correspondence of Richard Heath Dabney 1899-1920 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous papers of Richard Heath Dabney 1880-1958 (Box 1)
- Speeches and notes for speeches of Richard Heath Dabney 1889-1920 (Box 1)
- Newspapers clippings and pamphlets of Richard Heath Dabney 1890-1920 (Box 1)
- Worthless Stock Certificates of James Heath Dabney 1947 & various dates (Box 1)
  (In R. H. Dabney's possession)
- Correspondence of the Virginia Historical Society 1957-1970, 3 folders. ALS. (Box 1)
- Virginia Historical Society: Publishing Program 1961-1966 (Box 1)
- Virginia Historical Society: Minutes and Reports 1950-1969, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Virginia Historical Society: Business and Finance Papers 1965-1970 (Box 2)
- Virginia Historical Society: Miscellaneous Papers 1963-1970 (Box 2)
- University Press of Virginia: Correspondence 1963-1970, ALS. (Box 2)
- University Press of Virginia: Board Agendas, Minutes, Committee Reports 1963-1970, Items. (Box 2)
- University Press of Virginia: Reader Reports on books considered for publication 1963-1970, Items (Box 2)
- University Press of Virginia: List of Publications and Miscellaneous 1963-1970, Items (Box 3)
- Virginia: The New Dominion-Rough draft includes Forward; Chaps. 10; 11-19; 22; 27-30; and 31-35 [n.d.], 4 folders (Box 3)
- Virginia: The New Dominion-Rough draft includes Chaps. 36-End, plus Bibliography [n.d.] (Box 4)
- Virginia: The New Dominion- Rejected, Revised, and Corrected Chaps. [n.d.], 2 folders (Box 4)
- Virginia: The New Dominion- Typed copy includes Introduction materials; Chaps. 14; and 15-25 [n.d.], 2 folders (Box 4)
- Virginia: The New Dominion- Typed copy includes Chaps. 26-34; 35-End [n.d.], 2 folders (Box 5)
- Maps for Virginia: The New Dominion. [n.d.], Oversized (Box 5)
  - The Wilderness Road, Washington's Expedition to Ft. Le Bouf and Braddock's Defeat (Box 5)
    Originials and photographs
  - Virginia's Principal Geographic Regions (Box 5)
  - Virginia in the Civil War, 1861-1865 (Box 5)
  - Virginia at the time of the Indian Massacre of 1622 (Box 5)
  - Virginia Boundaries from 1609 to the Present Day (Box 5)
  - Virginia at the time of Bacon's Rebellion, 1676 (Box 5)
  - Virginia's urban corridor (Box 5)
- Virginia: The New Dominion- Setting copy includes 1-329 [n.d.], 2 folders (Box 5)
- Virginia: The New Dominion- Setting copy includes 330-End [n.d.], 3 folders (Box 6)
- Virginia: The New Dominion- Galley proofs includes Beginning - Chap. 27 [n.d.] (Box 6)
- Virginia: The New Dominion- Galley proofs includes Chaps. 28-End [n.d.] (Box 7)
- Virginia: The New Dominion- Galley proofs (final), 1-End [n.d.], 2 folders (Box 7)
- Virginia: The New Dominion- Galley proofs, pp. 1-End [n.d.], 2 folders (Box 8)